PR 312
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Jane Hoffer On the Beat Photograph Collection
Bulk, 1975-1979
1975-1979, 2011-2012
PR 312
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
0.5 Linear feet (1 Box)
This collection includes Jane Hoffer's photographs and interviews of women police officers between 1975 and 1979. The photos were later included in an exhibition called On the Beat 1975-1979: Women in the NYPD. An artist's book of the photos is also included.
Arrangement note
The photographs are arranged by subjects designated by the photographer. The non-photographic material (interviews, DVD, contact sheets and book) is foldered by format.
Related Material at Other Institutions
The New York City Police Museum also holds a collection of Jane Hoffer's photographs of police women.
Biographical/Historical note
Born in Canada, Jane Hoffer is a New York City based photographer who has been doing freelance work for over forty years. Hoffer attended McGill University where she started in painting and ended her graduate career with a dissertation on photographic essays. She received further training at the School of Visual Arts, the New School, and the International Center of Photography. Hoffer’s professional work has been primarily for non-profit organizations, including the Boys Choir of Harlem and Lincoln Center. In addition to her commercial work, Hofffer has pursued many artistic projects that have been exhibited throughout the city in both group and solo shows. SHe is currently a member of Professional Women Photographers.
The photographs in this collection document some of the first women police officers out on patrol in New York City. President Lyndon Johnson’s Crime Commission in 1967 reccomended sweeping changes to law enforcement training and hiring practices and called for for “new kinds of people” within in police forces: college graduates, women, minorities and skilled civilians. More and more women became patrol officers and moved into supervisory positions like station supervisor and detective. Further studies like the Kerner Commision’s 1968 Report of the National Advisory Commission on Civil Disorders and psychologist and Ford Foundation director Catherine Miller’s 1972 study, Women in Policing, contributed to the changing attitude toward women stepping out from behind the desk to take on more active policing duties. Policewomen faced fierce resistance from people outside their departments, as well as resentment from their fellow officers.
Hoffer began the project in the 1970’s when she was teaching photography at John Jay College of Criminal Justice when the photography collective to which she belonged, Women Photographers of New York, began a series of projects on working women. A colleague introduced her to Sergeant Joan Pearson, who then acquainted her with other female officers who were willing to be interviewed and photographed. Fascinated by the emerging roles of women in police work, Hoffer photographed officers, sergeants, and auxillaries in precinct houses, their patrol cars, and at the firing range. She also conducted extensive interviews of her subjects. The process continued for four years.
The photographs were exhibited at the SoHo Photo Gallery in 1980, the Wall Gallery at the John Jay College of Criminal Justice in 1989 and the New York City Police Museum in 2011, where the exhibit was called On the Beat 1975-1979: Women in the NYPD. The work was also published as an artist’s book, On the Beat 1975-79, which contains selections from the interviews as well as photographs.
Access Restrictions
Available by advance appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org. Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Provenance
Gift of Jane Hoffer, 2013.
Scope and Contents note
This collection contains photographs and other materials relating to On the Beat 1975-1979: Women in the NYPD, an exhibition of Hoffer’s photographs of some of the first female NYPD officers on the job. The photographs were taken between the years of 1975 to 1979. Photographs are arranged in the categories originally designated by the photographer, The subjects are named by the photographer as follows:
AUXILLARIES are two mounted officers, Susan Cohen and Susan Cooke and are pictured riding and caring for their horses.
COLLINS is Sergeant Barbara Collins who is depicted in her precinct, in dress blues, processing suspects and on patrol.
DECOYS is photographs of officers disguised as vulnerable citizens to act as a plant to lure muggers. They are mostly of Officer Rita Kaplowitz, who is a part of the street crime unit. Photographs show her being disguised as an older woman, at the station, and speaking to senior citizens in costume.
HARTMANN is Officer Mary Hartmann, who is shown assisting on EMT calls, turning out at roll call and on patrol in dress blues.
KNEDLEHAN is Officer Helen Knedlehan, an emergency service officer and instructor who is depicted teaching first aid and using the jaws of life on a car.
PEARSON is Sergeant Joan Pearson and is shown in the precinct house, on late night emergency calls, at the precinct cells and out on patrol doing “community relations.”
STANTON is Sergeant Marcia Stanton who is shown answering disturbance calls, in the precinct house and doing her make up.
SHAUGHNESSY is Officer Peggy O’Shaughnessy. She is shown at the shooting rage, on patrol, at the station, helping on an EMT call and in front of a burnt out building.
VAL DORNAN is Officer Val Dornan who is photographed in the locker room.
WALKER is shown on patrol and answering disturbance calls. Her first name and rank are not available.
WILSON is Ann Wilson, a physical instructor at the Police Academy. Prints show her teaching self defense to men and women, working with police recruits and instructing physical training.
There are 105 5x7” gelatin silver photographs, 26 11x14” gelatin silver photographers, and 8 contact sheets. The contact sheets includes images of “Women Partners,” for which there are no prints.
In addition to photographic prints and contact sheets, there is 1 DVD containing photographs and interviews, and an artist’s book On the Beat 1975-79 which contains photos and selections from the interviews. The interviews themselves are with a selection of nine of the subjects of the photos.
Note that some of the photographs in this collection are not represented in the book; there are also a few images that appear in the book but are not included in this collection.
- Auxillaries 11 x 14", [undated] (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Auxillaries 11 x 14", [undated] (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Auxillaries 5 x 7", c. 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Collins 11 x 14", 1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Collins 11 x 14", [undated] (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Collins 11 x 14", 1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Collins 5 x 7", c. 1975, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Decoys 11 x 14", 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Decoys 11 x 14", [undated] (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Decoys 5 x 7", c. 1976-1977, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Hartmann 11 x 14", [undated] (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Hartmann 11 x 14", [undated] (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Hartmann 11 x 14", [undated] (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Hartmann 5 x 7", [undated] (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Knedlehans 11 x 14", 1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Knedlehans 11 x 14", 1978 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Knedlehans 11 x 14", [undated] (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Knedlehans 5 x 7", 1978-1979, [undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Pearson 11 x 14", [undated] (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Pearson 5 x 7", c. 1975, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Stanton 11 x 14", [undated] (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Stanton 11 x 14", [undated] (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Stanton 11 x 14", [undated] (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Stanton 11 x 14", [undated] (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Stanton 5 x 7", c. 1976, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Shaughnessy 11 x 14", 1978 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Shaughnessy 11 x 14", 1978 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Shaughnessy 11 x 14", [undated] (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Shaughnessy 5 x 7", 1976, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Val Doran 11 x 14", [undated] (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Val Doran 11 x 14", [undated] (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Walker 11 x 14", [undated] (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Walker 11 x 14", 1978 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Walker 5 x 7", 1975, 1978, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Wilson 11 x 14", 1978 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Wilson 5 x 7", c. 1975, c. 1977, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Contact Sheets, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 37)
- DVD with photographs and interviews, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Interviews and Exhibit Card, 2011, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 39)
- On the Beat 1975-1979 Photographs by Jane Hoffer [book], 2012 (Box 1, Folder 40)